{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "In her twenties, this chemistry teacher worked at Chicago’s Hull House, before attending the Wharton School. As head of the National Consumers' League, this woman witnessed the Triangle Shirtwaist Factory Fire, leading to her appointment to the Committee of Safety. With a first lady, this woman organized the She-She-She camps in her highest office. For ten points, name this first female cabinet member, the Secretary of Labor under Franklin D. Roosevelt.",
      "answer": "Frances Perkins or Fannie Coralie Perkins"
    },
    {
      "question": "This proposal came out of a series of meetings with several Barnburners like Preston King and Hannibal Hamlin. Voting on this proposal immediately followed a proposal by Indiana Democrat William A. Wick to simply extend the line of the Missouri Compromise. Attached as a rider to a two million dollar appropriations bill to end the Mexican-American War, for ten points, what was this unsuccessful 1846 proposal by a Pennsylvania Democrat to ban slavery in the newly won territories?",
      "answer": "Wilmot Proviso"
    },
    {
      "question": "Michael VIII [[the eighth]] signed the Treaty of Nymphaeum [[nim-FAY-um]] with this polity, allowing trade concessions within the Byzantine Empire in exchange for fifty ships to push his claim to the throne. A Mongol siege of this state's port of Kaffa is hypothesized to be the origin of the Black Death in Europe. The 1768 Treaty of Versailles forced this Ligurian republic to cede Corsica to the Kingdom of France. For ten points, name this Northwestern Italian republic which fought many wars with the rival trade empire of Venice.",
      "answer": [
        "The Most Serene Republic of Genoa",
        "Serenìscima Repùbrica de Zêna",
        "or Repubblica di Genova",
        "or Res Publica Ianuensis",
        "also",
        "the Common Companions of Genoa",
        "or Compagna Communis Ianuensis"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The Kit Carson scouts were former members of this organization who defected to the United States. Backed by the People's Army, this force killed 3,000 pro-American citizens in Hue [[WAY]] during the Tet Offensive. A northern country supplied armaments to this organization via the Ho Chi Minh Trail. A prolonged guerilla war against U.S. forces was fought by, for ten points, what communist paramilitary group during a mid-20th century war?",
      "answer": [
        "Viet Cong",
        "National Liberation Front of South Vietnam",
        "or Mặt trận Dân tộc Giải phóng Miền Nam Việt Nam 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 8"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This general allied with Benito Juarez to battle the forces of Emperor Maximilian, eventually deposing and succeeding Sebastian Lerdo in his highest office. Factional strife between General Bernardo Reyes and the cientificos boiled over when this man declared himself winner of the presidency for the eighth time, after which he was the target of an uprising by Francisco Madero. For ten points, name this Mexican president immediately prior to the Mexican Revolution.",
      "answer": "Porfirio Díaz or José de la Cruz Porfirio Díaz Mori"
    },
    {
      "question": "Pausanias [[pow-SAN-ee-uss]] reported that the polis of Thebes claimed to have the bones of this hero. Roland's legendary sword Durendal was first forged for this man. Neoptolemus [[nee-op-TAH-leh-muss]] supposedly killed this man's infant son, Astyanax, by throwing him from the walls of a citadel. This man slew Patroclus while wearing the armor of his shield-brother. Achilles dragged the corpse of, for ten points, which Trojan hero and son of Priam?",
      "answer": "Hector"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man ironically published his memoir, Permanent Record, on September 17th which is also Constitution Day. This man is currently the head of the Board of Directors for the Freedom of the Press Foundation, having served in that role since 2016. In 2020, this man was finally granted asylum by the Russian government after fleeing the United States in 2013. For ten points, name this former NSA worker who leaked classified information about mass surveillance.",
      "answer": "Edward Snowden or Edward Joseph Snowden"
    },
    {
      "question": "Near this city, ancient Greeks founded a settlement named Hesperis [[heh-SPEH- riss]] in the sixth century BC. This city thrived as a center of the Roman province of Cyrenaica [[sy-ruh-NAY-kah]]. After Italy granted independence to its North African colony, Tripoli and this city served as the Kingdom of Libya’s two capitals. For ten points, name this Libyan city where Islamist militants attacked a U.S. diplomatic compound and killed four Americans, including Ambassador Chris Stevens.",
      "answer": "Benghazi ]"
    },
    {
      "question": "Isaac Newton theorized this substance was composed of corpuscles in his book Opticks. That particle theory of polarization of this substance was mainstream until Robert Hooke developed the \"pulse theory\" and compared this form of radiation to waves of water in his book Micrographia. Years later, Max Planck [[PLAHNK]] described this type of radiation as a wave that can gain or lose finite amounts of energy, known as \"quanta.\" For ten points, name this type of electromagnetic radiation that can be seen by human eyes.",
      "answer": "Visible Light 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 8"
    },
    {
      "question": "The name of this location in the Canaima [[kah-NAY-muh]] National Park is derived from the American aviator who first surveyed it from an airplane. In 2009, Venezuelan president Hugo Chávez argued for reinstating this geographical feature’s indigenous name, Kerepakupai Merú [[keh-reh-pah-KOO-pye meh-ROO]], which means “waterfall of the deepest place.” For ten points, name this world’s tallest uninterrupted waterfall which measures 3,212 feet.",
      "answer": [
        "Angel Fallsor Salto Ángel ],",
        "Kerepakupai Merú ] before mentioned 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 8"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An 1890 filibuster which planned to seize this region intended to appoint editor Warren Hastings as Governor-General. This region's \"South\" province rebelled against U.S. occupation during the Mexican-American War until the defeat of the rebels at San José del Cabo [[KAH-boh]]. It's not Nicaragua, but this region was captured by William Walker and incorporated into the Republic of Sonora. For ten points, identify this region now split into two Mexican states, where Walker occupied such cities as La Paz and Cabo San Lucas.",
        "answer": [
          "Baja ] California",
          "Baja California Sur"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1994, presidential candidate Luis Donaldo Colosio [[koh-LOH-syoh]] was assassinated in this major Baja California tourist city on the U.S. border.",
        "answer": "Tijuana"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man's unacknowledged abolitionist son, John Pierre, was born from a tryst with his Indian servant Mary Emmons. From 1808 to 1812, this man went on a self-imposed exile to England, where he befriended Utilitarian philosopher Jeremy Bentham. This New York lawyer received the second-highest amount of votes in one election, resulting in this man becoming vice president. For ten points, name this early leader of the Democratic- Republicans, the vice president under Thomas Jefferson.",
        "answer": "Aaron Burr Jr"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Burr's infamous duel with politician Alexander Hamilton occurred in which state's city of Weehawken?",
        "answer": "New Jersey"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Shortly after the death of this nation's \"King-Imam\" Ahmad bin Yahya, Egyptian- trained officers deposed the House of Rassid [[RAH-seed]]. This nation's port of Mocha [[MOH-kuh]] was a major stopping point in the international coffee trade. The Zaydi movement originated in this country's Saada Governate, which was the epicenter of a 2010s civil war that followed the rise of the Houthis. The Aden Emergency hastened the end of British rule in, for ten points, what Middle Eastern nation governed from Sana'a?",
        "answer": "Republic of Yemen"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "North Yemen, which was separated from South Yemen during the 1960s, was supported by which Egyptian dictator with supplies during a 1967 fight for independence?",
        "answer": "Gamal Abdel Nasser 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 8"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Rulers of this culture were known as wanax, and this culture is associated with a state known as Ahhiyawa [[ah-hee-YAH-wah]] in Hittite sources. The Lion’s Gate was excavated at the entrance to the namesake city of this culture. It‘s not Troy, but that city of this culture was excavated by Heinrich Schliemann [[SHLEE-mahn]], who publicized a golden death mask he found there. Michael Ventris deciphered the Linear B script used by, for ten points, what Ancient Greek culture of the Late Bronze Age?",
        "answer": "Mycenaeans ] or Mycenae"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "That golden death mask discovered by Schliemann was named for this mythical king of Mycenae, despite there being no evidence that it belonged to him.",
        "answer": [
          "Agamemnon",
          "Mask of Agamemnon"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Most of Beach Boys member Dennis Wilson's possessions were stolen by acolytes of this man. This man predicted the occurrence of a race war between Blacks and whites which he named after a Beatles song. A former lover and follower of this man, \"Squeaky\" Fromme, attempted to assassinate President Gerald Ford in 1975. For ten points, name this cult leader, the head of a namesake \"Family\" who murdered actress Sharon Tate.",
        "answer": [
          "Charles Manson or Charles Milles Manson",
          "or Charles Milles Maddox"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which Beatles song names Charles Manson's term for a race war between Blacks and whites which he predicted would lead to the end of the world?",
        "answer": "\"Helter Skelter\""
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The peace treaty ending this war led to a fifteen month \"Interim Peace\" and ceded one side's second-largest city of Viipuri [[VEE-poo-ree]]. This war saw the invention of Molotov [[MOH-loh-tohff]] cocktails. During this war, one side employed ski soldiers and a man called \"White Death,\" Simo Häyhä [[SEE-moh HY-ah]]. Despite taking Karelia [[kah- REH-lyah]], the Soviets failed to reach Helsinki in, for ten points, what World War Two-era conflict which saw Finland maintain its independence?",
        "answer": "Winter War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During the Winter War, the Finns utilized a defensive line named for what German- descended commander-in-chief who led the White forces in the Finnish Civil War?",
        "answer": "Carl Gustaf Emil Mannerheim 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 8"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 2013, rapper Killah P was murdered in this country by a member of the Golden Dawn, which lost its last Parliamentary seat in 2019. This country's New Democracy party was founded in 1974 after the fall of the Regime of the Colonels. Syriza [[sih-REE-zah]] party leader Alexis Tsipras [[TSIP-rahss]] led this country through a period of austerity bookended by its third E.U. bailout. For ten points, name this country whose Prime Minister Kyriakos Mitsotakis [[kee-ree-AH-kohss mit-so-TAH-kiss]] came to power in 2019.",
        "answer": [
          "Greece or Hellenic Republic",
          "or Elliniki Dimokratia",
          "or Hellas",
          "or Ellas",
          "or Ellada"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Greek debt crisis occurred under the governance of the PASOK [[PASS-ock]] party, which espouses this political and economic ideology, often represented by a red rose.",
        "answer": "Social-Democracy"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One account tells how this figure became divine shortly before visiting the Alban colonist Proculus [[PRAH-kyoo-luss]], who states that he turned into a whirlwind and went to the heavens. This man organized games to commit the abduction of the Sabine [[SAY- been]] women. This descendant of Aeneas [[ay-NEE-ahss]] may have killed his sibling after arguing on which of seven hills to found this figure's namesake city. The legendary first king of Rome was, for ten points, which twin brother of Remus?",
        "answer": "Romulus ]"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Romulus and Remus were reared by a female one of these creatures before being adopted by the shepherd Faustulus [[FOWST-yoo-luss]].",
        "answer": "Wolf"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Regarding losing U.S. presidential candidates, name the...",
      "prompt": "Concerning Regarding losing U.S. presidential candidates, name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Tennessee Democrat who was defeated in 2000 due to 537 votes from the state of Florida.",
          "answer": "Al Gore or Albert Arnold Al Gore Jr."
        },
        {
          "question": "Illinois senator who debated Abraham Lincoln years before losing to him in 1860.",
          "answer": "Stephen Arnold Douglas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Utah senator and former Governor of Massachusetts who unsuccessfully challenged Obama's second run for president.",
          "answer": "Mitt Romney or Willard Mitt Romney"
        },
        {
          "question": "Arizona conservative who lost to Lyndon B. Johnson in 1964.",
          "answer": "Barry Goldwater or Barry Morris Goldwater"
        },
        {
          "question": "Alabama governor who ran as a segregationist in 1968 and was later shot and paralyzed.",
          "answer": "George Wallace or George Corley Wallace Jr."
        },
        {
          "question": "Liberal Democrat who won only his home state of Minnesota in a landslide loss to Ronald Reagan in 1984.",
          "answer": "Walter \"Fritz\" Mondale or Walter Frederick Mondale"
        },
        {
          "question": "South Carolina Dixiecrat who finished third in 1948, losing to both Dewey and Truman.",
          "answer": "Strom Thurmond or James Strom Thurmond Sr."
        },
        {
          "question": "Governor of Ohio who ran on a ticket with FDR in 1920, losing to Republican Warren G. Harding.",
          "answer": "James M. Cox or James Middleton Cox 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 8 Medieval English Monarchs at War"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "England marches to war! Name the...",
      "prompt": "Answer these questions about England marches to war! Name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "King whose conquest of England in 1066 is depicted in the Bayeaux [[\"Bayou\"]] Tapestry.",
          "answer": [
            "William the Conqueror or William I",
            "William the Bastard"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Six-wived King of England who defeated the French at the Battle of the Spurs.",
          "answer": "Henry VIII"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"Great\" King of Wessex who defeated the Great Heathen Army at Edington.",
          "answer": "Alfred the Great"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"Hammer of the Scots\" who defeated William Wallace at Falkirk.",
          "answer": [
            "Edward I",
            "Edward Longshanks"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "King whose longbowmen devestated the French at Agincourt [[ah-jin-KOHR]].",
          "answer": "Henry V"
        },
        {
          "question": "Father of the \"Black Prince\" who dealt with the Plague and the early phases of the Hundred Years War.",
          "answer": "Edward III or Edward of Windsor"
        },
        {
          "question": "King of Denmark who deposed Aethelred the Unready to take the throne of England.",
          "answer": [
            "Sweyn ] Forkbeard or Sveinn Haraldsson tjúguskegg",
            "be lenient on pronunciation"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Son of Isabella of Angoulême [[ahn-goo-LEHM]] taken prisoner after the Battle of Lewes [[LOOS]] during the Second Barons' War.",
          "answer": "Henry III or Henry of Winchester 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 8"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Qing Dynasty",
      "prompt": "Concerning the Qing [[CHING]] Dynasty of 1644 to 1912, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Massive country which it controlled.",
          "answer": [
            "China",
            "Empire of China",
            "Imperial China",
            "Zhōngguó"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Resource-rich region of Northeast Asia where the Qing dynasty originated.",
          "answer": [
            "Manchuria",
            "Manchu",
            "or Manchurians",
            "Dōngsānshěng",
            "or Guangdong",
            "Jurchens"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Two wars named for a narcotic, both victories for the British Empire over the Qing.",
          "answer": "Opium Wars"
        },
        {
          "question": "Last native dynasty destabilized by internal rebellion and overthrown by the Qing.",
          "answer": "Ming Dynasty"
        },
        {
          "question": "Last emperor of the Qing who was placed on the throne of the Japanese puppet state, Manchukuo [[MAN-CHOO-KWOH]].",
          "answer": [
            "Emperor Puyi",
            "Henry Puyi",
            "Xuantong Emperor",
            "Yaozhi"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Rebellion launched by civil servant Hong Xiuquan [[SHOO-CHWAN]], who attempted to found a Heavenly Kingdom.",
          "answer": [
            "Taiping Rebellion or Taiping Civil War",
            "or Taiping Revolution"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "\"Dowager Empress\" who controlled the Qing government through the Hundred Days Reform and died in 1908.",
          "answer": [
            "Cixi ] or Empress Dowager Cixi",
            "or Cíxī Tàihòu"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1911 Revolution that collapsed Qing rule, resulting in the disastrous rise of Yuan Shikai.",
          "answer": "Xinhai Revolution 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 8"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this colony, former indentured servant Maryn Adriansen committed a massacre of natives during Kieft's War. The Treaty of Breda formally handed over this colony to Charles II's England, and it was led by Director-General Peter (20 pts)",
        "Stuyvesant [[STY-veh-sahnt]]. Using a cache of trade goods, including glass beads, Peter Minuit bought the island of (10 pts)",
        "Manhattan for this North American colonial venture. New Amsterdam served as the capital of, for ten points, what Dutch colonial venture in the Mid-Atlantic region of the modern U.S.?"
      ],
      "answer": "New Netherland or Nieuw Nederland"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) While happening upon this event, Beat poet Allen Ginsberg allegedly said “it’s about time that we did something to assert ourselves.” Sylvia Riviera has been mythologized as the person that “threw the first brick at [this event].” This event, which occurred a week after Judy (20 pts)",
        "Garland’s death, broke out after lesbian Stormé DeLarverie [[stor-MAY deh-LAR-veh-ree]] was arrested and assaulted by (10 pts)",
        "New York police. For ten points, name this 1969 LGBTQ “riot” that began at a Greenwich Village gay bar."
      ],
      "answer": "Stonewall Inn Riot"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This war likely led to the victory of Lord Salisbury's Conservatives in the \"Khaki Election.\" A modified Maxim gun known as the \"Pom-Pom\" was introduced during this war, and its last two years degenerated into guerilla warfare under generals like Jan [[YAHN]] (20 pts)",
        "Smuts. The sieges of Kimberly and Mafeking [[MAH- feh-king]] occurred during this war, which was named for (10 pts)",
        "Dutch settlers of Africa. The Transvaal and the Orange Free State were incorporated into South Africa following, for ten points, what turn of the twentieth century conflict?"
      ],
      "answer": "Second Boer War"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Isser Harel called for a two year manhunt in this nation which aimed to bring Nazi war criminal Josef Mengele to justice. The dictator José Gaspar Rodríguez de Francia was known in this country as \"El Supremo.\" The Battle of Cerro Corá [[SEH- roh koh-RAH]] saw the death of this country's president Francisco Solano (20 pts)",
        "López, ending the six-year-long War of the Triple Alliance that pitted this country against three neighbors: Brazil, Argentina, and Uruguay. (10 pts)",
        "For ten points, name this landlocked South American country."
      ],
      "answer": "Republic of Paraguay or Republica del Paraguay 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 8"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Due to failing to predict these events, the semi-mythical astrologers Hsi [[SEE]] and Ho were executed by a Xia [[SHYAH]] emperor. According to Herodotus, one of these events stopped a war between the Lydians and Medes since it was interpreted as a (20 pts)",
        "divine signal. An 1135 one of these phenomena coincided with the death of Henry I of England, associating these celestial events as an ill omen for rulers. The birth of (10 pts)",
        "Muhammad coincided with, for ten points, what type of celestial event in which the moon blocks all or part of the sun?"
      ],
      "answer": "Solar Eclipse"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Days prior to an event at this site, Mikhail Gorbachev met with a world leader for a summit at a nearby locale at the Great Hall of the People. A gathering in this location was precipitated by the death of the reformist Hu (20 pts)",
        "Yaobang [[HOO-YAO- BAHNG]]. Constructed during the Ming Dynasty in 1415, perhaps the most iconic photo taken at this location was of an unidentified man (10 pts)",
        "blocking tanks on a road. For ten points, name this Chinese location that was the site of mass protests and a massacre in 1989."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Tiananmen Square",
        "Tiananmen Square protests",
        "Tiananmen Square massacre"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Andres Segovia commissioned a composer from this nation, Heitor Villa-Lobos [[VEE-yah LOH-bohs]], to write a series of études for classical guitar. This nation's commuter rail network is credited with spreading one musical genre out from the Estácio neighborhood. (20 pts)",
        "Astrud Gilberto sang on \"Girl from Ipanema,\" which launched this nation's genre of Bossa Nova to worldwide popularity. Choro and (10 pts)",
        "Samba both originated in, for ten points, what country's city of Rio de Janeiro?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Federative Republic of Brazil or República Federativa do Brasil",
        "Kingdom of Brazil",
        "or Reino do Brasil"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "Li Mi of the Sui [[SWEH]] Dynasty constructed 300 of the \"Whirlwind\" variety of these machines to be placed on ships. During the Hrushevskoho [[hroo-shehv- SKOH-hoh]] Street riots, a Kievan mob built one of these machines to hurl Molotov (*) cocktails at government buildings. The Mangonel was an early form of this siege engine brought from China, arriving in Medieval (*) Europe by the 9th century. For ten points, what siege engine used a counterweight to fling objects?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Trebuchet or Trebucket",
        "specific examples, such as the Traction Trebuchet",
        "Counterpoise Trebucet",
        "Mangonel before mentioned"
      ]
    }
  ]
}